Guide to the Records of the National Jewish Welfare Board, undated, 1889-1995 (bulk 1917-1990) *I-337
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
- Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers, undated, 1904-1995 (bulk 1920-1980); 919 linear feet.
  - Series A: Program Services, 1904-1989 (bulk 1930-1980); 234.46 linear feet.
    - Subseries 11: Publications, 1919-1976 (bulk 1945-1960); 13.5 linear feet.
      Additional materials include correspondence, negatives (located in Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup), copyright certificates, conference proceedings, Photostats (located in Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup), and war effort publications.
    - Subseries 12: Statistics and Research Department, 1930-1987; 15 linear feet.
      This subseries is arranged as follows: Annual Reports Worksheets (1930-1977), Annual Reports Supplements (1941-1974), Basic Records (1945-1953), Building Reports (1947-1959), Manuals (1944-1957), Personnel Reports (1968-1971), Questionnaires (1954-1973), Salary Reports (1948, 1964-1974), Seminar Reports (1976), Statistical Reports (1941-1966), Surveys (1946-1947, 1965-1967, 1973-1974), Edward Kagen: General Files (1958-1987), and Edward Kagen: Surveys (1975-1977, 1982-1983, 1986). Arranged chronologically and alphabetically.
      This subseries consists of statistics relating to almost all aspects of JWB such as salaries, facilities, personnel, and annual reports. Of special interest is Samuel Asofsky's thesis entitled "Least squares analysis of salaries paid in 1948 to full-time professional staff workers in JCCs."
      Also included are Edward Kagen's files as consultant for statistics and research and as Director of the Florence Heller - JWB Research Center.
      Included are annual reports, correspondence, personnel reports, surveys, questionnaires, data analysis, budgets, pamphlets, theses, dissertations, spreadsheets, punch cards, and micro discs.
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: JCC/Series A: Program Services/Subseries 2: Florence Heller Research Center and Subseries 10: Program Development and Research Services.
    - Subseries 13: Vocational Guidance, 1926-1942 (bulk 1939-1942); 1.75 linear feet.
      The subseries reflects how JWB sought to help those new to the JWB field and soldiers returning home find gainful employment in their communities. Types of material found are correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, questionnaires, and pamphlets.
    - Subseries 14: Youth Programming, 1923-1969 (bulk 1940-1968); 21.25 linear feet.
      This subseries is arranged into the following subsubseries: Alphabetical Files (1930-1968, bulk 1940-1966), Jewish College Youth ([circa 1947]-1969, bulk 1968-1969), Jewish Youth Councils (1936-1953), National Jewish Youth Conference (1947-1956), Subject Files (1923-1954 (bulk 1949-1952), White House Conference on Youth (1948-1961, bulk 1950-1951), and Youth Committee (1942-1952). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
      The Youth Programming Department's material highlights how JWB assisted the various JCCs and YMHAs in developing valuable and instructive programs for the Jewish youth in their communities. The Jewish College Youth Files reflects how JWB reached out to Jewish College students and tried to determine what issues were paramount in their lives. The Jewish Youth Councils shows the manner in which JWB worked with young leaders to provide a significant opportunity for both the youth and the future of the Jewish community. The first White House Conference on Youth occurred in 1909 under President Roosevelt. The 1950 conference developed 5 goals:
      1. bring together in usable form pertinent knowledge related to the development of children and indicate areas in which further knowledge is needed
      2. examine the environment in which children are growing up, with a view to determining its influence upon them
      3. study the ways in which the home, the school, the church, the law, welfare agencies, and other social institutions, individually and cooperatively, are serving the needs of children
      4. formulate, through cooperative efforts of laymen and specialists, proposals for the improvement of parental, environmental and institutional influences on children
      5. suggest means whereby these proposals may be communicated to the people and put into action. 15
      The files document JWB's efforts with the White House in order to help improve the lives of children within the United States.
      Of particular interest within the alphabetical files and the subject files are the materials pertaining to the National Commission of Children and Youth, teen-agers, the handbook for Young Judeans, 1927 and the Youth Movement articles. The alphabetical files and the subject files are the same types of material and may overlap in subject matter.
      Types of material found are conference proceedings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, training courses, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, studies, minutes, play scripts, newspapers, surveys, program bulletins, teaching materials, Passover material, agendas, member lists.
      15 National Jewish Youth Conference Report of Mid-Century White House Conference of Children and Youth, February 15, 1950, American Jewish Historical Society.
  - Series B: Field Services, undated, 1911-1995 (bulk 1921-1980); 371 linear feet.
    This series is arranged into six subseries as follows: 1) Community Services; 2) Community Studies; 3) Field Reports; 4) Geographic Files; 5) Regional Area Files; and 6) Regional Area Offices.
    This series documents JWB's relationship with the various affiliated Centers throughout the United States and the World. The support services that were available to the Centers are clearly defined and highlighted throughout the records.
    - Subseries 1: Community Services, 1945-1984 (bulk 1960-1978); 117 linear feet.
      This subseries is arranged as follows: Emanuel Berlatsky Director of Community Services (1961-1968); Director of JWB Services in Large Metropolitan Communities (1945-1984, bulk 1961-1973), Jack Boeko Community Consultant; Staff Coordinator New Jersey Section (1953-1976, bulk 1972-1974), Arthur Brodkin Bureau of Personnel and Training; Regional Consultant New York State Section; Community Consultant; Staff Coordinator Mid-Atlantic Region; Staff Coordinator Southern Area; Consultant on Placement of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation Staff (1953-1982, bulk 1973-1980), Sy Colen Community Consultant; Staff Coordinator Mid-Atlantic Area (1945-1981, bulk 1963-1970), Harold Dinerman Director of Community Services; Director of Community Consultation Services (1949-1976, bulk 1967-1973), Director's Office (Mostly Emanuel Berlatsky) (1944-1972), Alfred Dobrof Community Consultant (1979-1981), Englewood, NJ (1967-1970, bulk 1969-1970), Rabbi Philip Goodman Community Consultant to Small Jewish Communities (1966-1973, bulk 1969), Barry Hantman Community Consultant (1973-1978), Zev Hymowitz Community Consultant (1956-1989, bulk 1988), Mitchell Jaffe Community Consultant; Assistant Director Community Services; Director of Community Services (1957-1988, bulk 1974-1988), Recreation/Leisure Reports (1939-1962), Larry Szpirglas Community Consultant (1954-1986, bulk 1973-1984), Earl Yaillen Community Consultant (1970-1980). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
      Up until 1960 the Field Services Department carried out the community services function with field secretaries in place. In 1963 Field Services changed focus and became Regional Consultation. The field secretaries had previously traveled to various organizations all over the country and Canada to assist the executives and staff of these centers in any way that they could. Reports were written and feedback given. During the decade 1960 - 1970 the concentration shifted to particular communities throughout the country. Field Secretaries became Regional Consultants and their areas were now more concentrated to one district which they were to visit more frequently, as well as the 12 staff members who were spread out and assigned to Chicago, Newark, Boston, Philadelphia, San Francisco, Atlanta, and New York. After the JWB study of 1970 the department changed again to Department of Community Services and again roughly ten years later to Community Consultation Services. And the focus changed again to more national coverage. JWB states that
      "it is the function of the JWB Community Consultant to be in regular communication with his communities through a variety of methods, including telephone, correspondence, other normal associations such as professional meetings and conferences and focused community visitations. Although there is no longer a pattern of regular visits, there is a pattern of regular communication in order to determine how we can be most helpful, including visitations when necessary. At a minimum, every JWB Consultant is in telephone communication with the executives of the centers no less than once a month."16
      Today the JWB is known as the JCC Association and according to their website:
      "This year, JCC Association celebrated 80 years of assisting JCCs in responding to changing conditions and challenges. From its New York headquarters and its Western Region and Israel offices, JCC Association has provided leadership in the areas of staff recruitment and training, lay leadership development, field research, professional conferences, and workshops, consultation, publications, and specialized programming, enabling each of its constituent JCCS to better serve the needs of its members and community."17
      The subseries reflects how JWB offered the affiliated Y's, JCCs, and other organizations a link to JWB's headquarters and its many functions. Building plans and architects, program ideas, policy changes, and help finding and hiring new staff were all available for the asking. They also offered conferences for executives in small, intermediate, and large cities.
      Emanuel Berlatsky's files highlight his work within the various Jewish communities, the Colleges and Universities with social work programs, and the Field Services Committee. Jack Boeko's material shows his involvement with the Biennial Conventions, and Intermediate City Center Executive Seminars. Arthur Brodkin's files reflect his participation with the Biennial Conventions, the Jewish communities, and the Health and Physical Education Department. Sy Colen's files highlight his work with Belgian Youth, the Biennial Convention, and Jewish communities. Harold Dinerman's records show his involvement with area councils and the Jewish communities. The Englewood, NJ material reflects the study conducted in that Community. Philip Goodman's files consist of Sherut Vol. 1 - Vol. 3. Barry Hantman's records highlight his work with the Intermediate City Center Executive Seminars and the Nine Cities Conference. Mitchell Jaffe's documents consist of community files from his work as Community Consultant and as Director of Community Services. Also included are the subject files he used as reference material. Larry Szpirglas's files show his community work, resources files and his involvement with the Large Intermediate City Center Executive Seminars and the Nine Cities Conference.
      Of special interest are: Morris Levin's A Survey of Research and Program Developments Involving Jewish Adolescents and the Implications for JCC Service Chicago, IL 1969 (Berlatsky, Emanuel/Communities: Individual/Chicago, IL/1969); Papers submitted to Journal of Jewish Communal Service (Director's Office/Journal of Jewish Communal Service); National Commission for Social Work and Council on Social Work Education/Careers (Director's Office/Minutes and Organizations); Self Studies done by Centers for Leisure-Time Activities (Recreation/Leisure Reports)
      Material in this subseries consists of photographs (located in Audio-Visual Subgroup), correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas, field reports, building plans (located in Oversized Materials Subgroup), profile transmission notices, programs, bulletins, memoranda, studies, and budgets.
      16 The Service Needs of Jewish Community Centers and How These are Being Met, 1972, I-337 NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
      17 Jewish Community Centers Association, Since the Sixties, http://www.jcca.org/today.html, June 6, 2003.
      Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series A: Governing Body/Subseries 1: Annual Meetings; Subgroup I: Governance/Series D: Conventions and Committees/Subseries 1: Biennials; Subgroup II: JCC/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 3: Field Reports; Subgroup IV: Affiliated Organizations.
      Restrictions: Several folders are restricted due to the subject matter.
      Note: JWB Miscellaneous Box 8 is located at end of entire collection. The material relates to the Sy Colen and Mitchell Jaffe Files.
    - Subseries 2: Community Studies, undated, 1921-1964 (bulk 1940-1955); 16 linear feet.
      This material pertains to surveys of Jewish communities, self-studies of JCCs, and studies of other Jewish organizations. (The purpose of these studies was to evaluate the services of JCCs by analyzing Jewish population trends, determining how Jewish people spent leisure time, appraising existing JCC programs and studying Jewish participation in activities sponsored by other organizations.18) The files dating from 1921 to 1950 include many actual studies and surveys; after 1950 relatively few appear. The files from 1951 on consist mainly of correspondence, and some of these files contain only 1 or 2 memoranda and letters. Some states, such as Montana, Vermont, and Wyoming, are not represented at all, while for others a large amount of material is included. New York and Pennsylvania (particularly Philadelphia and Pittsburgh: the Irene Kaufmann Center and Settlement) are strongly represented. Some material on Canada (mainly Toronto) is also included, as is a small file (1 document) on South Africa. Materials of note include "A Study of Negro Housing in Atlanta Georgia, 1940 - 1956." (This was a sociology research paper written by a Dartmouth student.) Also of note are an YMHA Golden Anniversary Souvenir Book (1890-1940) for Louisville Kentucky and a 1953 JCC self-study manual, which provides guidance on the purpose and scope of surveys and studies. Finally, the early studies, such as a 1924 study of educational and recreational resources and needs of the Jewish Community on New York's Lower East side, provide an interesting look at Jewish communities in the early part of the 20th century. The material includes surveys, studies, maps, field reports, correspondence, clippings, photographs (located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup), charts, maps, and blueprints (located in the Oversized Materials Subgroup.)
      18 JCC Self-Study Manual, 1953, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series A: Program Services/Subseries 5: Jewish Media Service; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 1: Community Services, Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 4: Geographic Files, Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 6: Regional Area Offices.
      Restrictions: New Jersey, Newark: Seth Boyden, Groups I and II (restrict until 2023); New York, Bronx, 1934-1936 (restrict until 2011); Massachusetts, Greater Boston YMHA
    - Subseries 3: Field Reports, 1919-1980 (bulk 1921-1965); 40 linear feet.
      Field reports from JCCs and YM & YWHA's (1921-1967, 1969-1980), Anniversaries and Annual Reports (1919-1965), Regional Sections (1939-1943), Related Organizations (1928-1961), and Summary Field Work (1927-1928, 1930-1931, 1939). Arranged chronologically and alphabetically.
      The subseries documents the work of the various field secretaries throughout the country and Canada. The period of 1921 to 1954 is especially rich in content and reflects the procedural changes made by the JWB during the course of the 33 years that the records cover. Massachusetts, New York and Pennsylvania have the largest concentration of material for all time spans. Also evident are the day-to-day problems faced by the organization and what, if anything, JWB was able to do to help them. After 1954, fewer visits were made by the field secretaries to the communities due to change in focus by JWB and the Department of Field Services. The drop-off in need by the centers may have been the catalyst. The Summary Field Work material documents each field visit performed by the field secretaries noting date of visit, location, and purpose. Of special interest is the Hecht House in Dorchester, MA; Baron de Hirsch Fund and Woodbine, NJ; New York Office of Civil Defense 1941-1953; Williamsburg YMHA NYC Brooklyn 1922-1954; Syracuse, NY 1922-1954; Philadelphia, PA 1922-1954 (Field Reports); Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds; Federation of Jewish Philanthropies (Related Organizations); and First NJWB Annual Report 1919 (Anniversaries and Annual Reports).
      Types of documents found are field reports, summaries of field visits, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, annual reports, correspondence, and anniversary booklets.
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: JCC/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 1: Community Services; Subgroup IV: Affiliated Organizations/Series A: National Affiliated Organizations - Series D: YMHA.
      Note: Miscellaneous box 17 added to the end of the collection relates to the Field Reports Material.
    - Subseries 4: Geographic Files, undated, 1938-1968 (bulk 1946-1966); 13 linear feet.
      Arranged alphabetically by regional section, state, and city.
      JWB divided the country into the following geographical areas (which were known as Sections, or Regions): Middle Atlantic, Midwest, New England, New Jersey, New York Metropolitan, New York State, Southern, and Western States. The Regions' mission was to promote close relationships between JCCs, Ys, and other organizations; to coordinate programs within organizations; to stimulate organization of new JCCs; and to aid member agencies in development and improvement of programs so that the agencies could contribute to the intellectual, religious, social and physical well being of Jews and Americans. Regions were visited by Community Consultants, who provided assistance and guidance to JCCs, Ys, Federations, Armed Forces Services Committees, and other organizations. Community Consultants served as the primary means for channeling JWB services to communities and provided both community planning and educational programming assistance.
      This subseries consists of correspondence, field reports, newsletters, maps, charts, diagrams, and blueprints (located in Oversized Materials subgroup) dealing with JCCs within the regional sections. (Some material on Canada is also included.) Of particular note are the Philadelphia camping materials in the Middle Atlantic Section, "Proceedings of an Institute on Models for Service to Jewish Families by JCCs," in the 1968 Santa Barbara California files, and the Bridgeport Connecticut survey material, which includes "Highlights in Center History, 1912-1957."
      Note: For Pittsburgh, Erie, and Westchester Penn., see the Midwest Section. For El Paso, Texas, see the Western States section. The remainder of Texas can be found in the Southern section.
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 3: Field Reports; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 5: Regional Area Files; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 6: Regional Area Offices.
    - Subseries 5: Regional Area Files, 1931-1966, 1968-1970 (bulk 1948-1962); 18 linear feet.
      Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by region.
      This subseries documents activities within the Regions. Files on the Metropolitan and National Associations of Jewish Center Workers (NAJCW) and the National Council of YM and YWHAs of Canada are also included here. Materials of note include NAJCW's 1953 statement of principles and a Louis Kraft article on "NAJCW-35 Years." Other highlights include Keynotes, the Midwest Section's newsletter, and the Proceedings of the Institute for Teens, in NAJCW's 1966 file, and a file on the New York State Section's 50th anniversary annual meeting. (This file includes statistics on the Centers and Ys in New York State.) Also of note are Convention materials, which provide summaries of each section's activities. (The New England section's 50th annual convention program contains acknowledgements from New England Congresspeople.) Included here are field reports, correspondence, meeting and biennial materials, section constitutions, photograph (located in the Audio-Visual Materials subgroup), certificates, and statements (located in the Oversized Materials subgroup.)
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 3: Field Reports; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 4: Geographic Files; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 6: Regional Area Offices.
      Restrictions: Southern Section: Lebovits, H.; Western Section: Kanner, Ted
    - Subseries 6: Regional Area Offices, undated, 1911-1995 (bulk 1945-1975); 169 linear feet.
      Atlanta Office (undated, 1948-1976; bulk 1951-1953, 1970-1974), Boston Office (undated, 1952, 1969-1978), Denver Office (1946-1947, 1951-1957, 1959-1975; bulk 1964-1975), Federations (1919-1935, 1938-1944; bulk 1939-1944), Middle Atlantic (undated, 1919, 1922-1977; bulk 1955-1970), Midwest (1939-1967, 1969-1972; bulk 1951-1972), New England (undated, 1911-1979; bulk 1948-1970), New Jersey (undated, 1947-1981; bulk 1962-1976), New York Metropolitan (undated, 1915-1995; bulk 1952-1973), New York State (undated, 1953-1969; bulk 1963-1967), Phoenix Office (1981-1985), Washington Office (undated, 1943-1982; bulk 1960-1982), Western Area (undated, 1965-1983, 1985; bulk 1973-1981). Mainly arranged alphabetically: some portions are arranged chronologically.
      Federations: the earlier files are arranged alphabetically, while the 1939-1944 files are arranged first chronologically and then alphabetically; New York Metropolitan Area: Organization Files from 1958 on are chronological, then alphabetical. The majority of the New York Metropolitan Area Subject Files are arranged by date. (Many of these files actually cover a broader range of years than may at first be apparent. For example, the "1952" file ranges from 1951 to 1955, with the bulk of the material falling in 1952.) Approximately 6 feet of the Subject Files are arranged alphabetically. New York State Area: Herman Sainer's Administration on Aging files are arranged in three chronological subsets, while the Subject files are arranged in five chronological subsets: 1960-1962, 1964-1965, 1965-1966, 1966-1967, and 1967-1968. (As with the New York Metropolitan Area, a wider range of years is actually covered in each subset.)